Matheus Ferreira

Data Analyst | Researcher | Political Scientist

Website

https://mathpol.github.io/mferreira/

Education

March/2018 - August/2022

Ph.D. Political Science

Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG)

Public Opinion • Political Behavior • Electoral Studies • Methodology

March/2014 - September/2016

M.Sc. in Social Science

Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)

Public Opinion • Political Behavior • Electoral Studies

March/2009 - April/2013

B.Sc. in Social Science

Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)

Public Opinion • Political Behavior
• Electoral Studies

Interests

- Data Analysis
- Data Science
- Computational Social Science
- Political Science
- Public Policy

Hard Skills

- Quantitative and Qualitative Methodology
- Scientific Computing
- Programming Language (R, RMarkdown)

Biography

Ph.D. candidate in Political Science at UFMG and researcher at the Center for the Study of Political Behavior (CECOMP). Intern researcher at the Public Policies Department at Fundação João Pinheiro (FJP). He works in the Public Opinion, Political Behavior, Public Policy, and Education research fields, using quantitative and qualitative methodologies. Academic CV

Professional Experience

BITSS Catalyst

2021 - current

Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in the Social Sciences

I work in promoting the transparency of Social Sciences Researches, organizing events, training courses and tutorials.

Researcher | Ph.D. Intern

10/2021 - current

Public Policy Department Fundação João Pinheiro (FJP)

I evaluate the public policies effectiveness in the State of Minas Gerais, especially those with an impact on Education. Recently I evaluated the effectiveness of the Minas Comunica II program, using secondary data from different sources (data from INEP and the Minas Gerais Social Responsibility Index). I also contributed to the Digital Transformation program, which develops programming routines for the Foundation's data management.

Researcher | Ph.D.

03/2018 - current

Political Science Graduate Program and Center for the Study of Political Behavior (Prof. Mario Fuks) Federal University of Minas Gerais

I research in the Public Opinion and Political Behavior fields.

Consulting

05/2021 - 08/2021

Politize!

I participated in the elaboration of "Leadership and Citizenship" course for teachers from the State Education System.

Temporary Lecturer - Social Science

07/2018 - 12/2018

Social Science Department Federal University of Juiz de Fora

Professor of three subjects: "Introduction to Political Science", "Public Policies and Society" and "Cultural Studies".

Sociology and Philosophy Teacher

03/2013 - 12/2017

Santos Anjos School and Equipe School

I worked as a high school teacher for 5 years.

Complementary Training

• (2021) Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in the Social Sciences (BITSS - Berkeley

- Office and Google Documents
- Data versioning (GitHub)

Soft Skills

- Proactive
- Leadership
- Critical sense
- Team work
- Autonomy
- Communicative

Contact

- \square (55) +32 9 8853-9670
- ferreira.dcp@gmail.com
- github.com/mathpol
- in linkedin.com/matheus_ferreira

University of California)

- (2021) Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (SICSS)
- (2021) Monitor Programming Course in R Language
- (2021) Introduction to Bayesian Inferences Online IBPAD 5 hours
- (2020) Public Data: use of public statistics for social research CECAPS/UFMG April 14^{th} May 30^{th} .

Published Academic Papers

- FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça; FUKS, Mario; SMITH, Amy Erica. A
 Conversion to the Right: The Case of the 2018 Election of Jair Bolsonaro in Brazil.
 Latin American Studies Association (Forthcoming).
- TAMAKI, Eduardo Ryo; VENTURELLI, Gustavo; FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça. Loudmouth, Sharp Tongue: The Use of Debasing Language by Brazil's President Jair Bolsonaro. In: Dissing and Derision: Political Leaders' Vulgar Rhetoric and Ridicule around the Globe. Springer Nature Singapore Pte Ltd. (Forthcoming).
- FERREIRA, Matheus G. M; COSTA, Gustavo Paccelli da. E depois do fim? Transições políticas na crise da democracia contemporânea. Contemporânea Revista de Sociologia da UFSCar. 2021.
- TAMAKI, Eduardo Ryo; MENDONÇA, Ricardo Fabrino; FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça. The Symbolic Construction of a Messiah: Jair Bolsonaro's Public, Christian Discourse. In: When Politicians Talk: The Cultural Dynamics of Public Speaking. Springer Nature Singapore Pte Ltd. Print scheduled to 2021.
- FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça; FUKS, Mario. O hábito de frequentar cultos como mecanismo de mobilização eleitoral: o voto evangélico em Bolsonaro em 2018. Revista Brasileira de Ciência Política, n. 34, 2021.
- FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça. Os fundamentos religiosos do Capitalismo e da Democracia e uma preocupação com a liberdade: um diálogo entre Tocqueville e Weber. Numen, v. 23, n. 2, 2020.
- FERREIRA, Matheus Gomes Mendonça; JÚNIOR, Fernando Tavares. DE 2013 A 2016: AS RUAS E RESSIGNIFICAÇÕES POLÍTICAS. **CSOnline**, n. 22, 2016.

Awards and Grants

- (2022) Best overall paper in the VII Fórum Brasileiro de Pós-Graduação em Ciência Política
- (2022) Best Paper in Culture and Political Behavior Work Group in the VII Fórum Brasileiro de Pós-GRaduação em Ciência Política
- (2022) Catalyst Grant for Advancing Transparent, Reproducible, and Ethical Research Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in the Social Sciences (BITSS).